<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on William Morgan</title>
    <link>/willsmorgan.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on William Morgan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/willsmorgan.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Discussion - Mostly Harmless Econometrics: Chapter 2</title>
      <link>/willsmorgan.github.io/post/book-discussion-mostly-harmless-econometrics-chapter-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/willsmorgan.github.io/post/book-discussion-mostly-harmless-econometrics-chapter-2/</guid>
      <description>Chapter 2: The Experimental IdealAngrist and Pischke begin building the foundation for concepts fundamental to causal inference in the second chapter of Mostly Harmless Econometrics. It opens with an anecdote about a 1962 experiment conducted to assess the effects of an early-intervention in preschoolers, highlighting the project’s excellent randomized design. The study itself was used as evidence for the creation of the Head Start preschool program but for us it matters because it reflects the value of random assignment in research design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Discussion - Mostly Harmless Econometrics: Chapter 1</title>
      <link>/willsmorgan.github.io/post/book-discussion-mostly-harmless-econometrics-chapter-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/willsmorgan.github.io/post/book-discussion-mostly-harmless-econometrics-chapter-1/</guid>
      <description>Motivation This will be part of a series of posts I am writing to help bring my chops on causal inference up to par. Since I have not taken a formal course on the subject and I won&amp;rsquo;t be able to for some time, self-study is my only option. Fortunately I&amp;rsquo;ve been recommended quite a few resources from my instructors, one of which being Mostly Harmless Econometrics by Joshua D.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing Random Forests in R</title>
      <link>/willsmorgan.github.io/post/parallelizing-random-forests-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/willsmorgan.github.io/post/parallelizing-random-forests-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Recently I’ve been working on a project with the goal of understanding how students choose between course modalities (online or in-person). My goal so far has been to test a handful of models to come up with the most accurate way of predicting the likelihood that a student will take a course online. Hopefully, this best-performing model would offer some interpretability so that I can see which variables offer the most predictive power.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>